These days, whenever I look at the back
of my beloved 7-month-old baby's head,
this little swirl of tiny hairs reminds
me of one of the most ridiculously named
facts in math, the hairy ball theorem. I
promise this is a genuinely serious bit
of math, where informally the statement
is that if you have a ball that's
covered in hair and you try to comb it
down, there is no way to do it without
having the hair stick up at least one
point. For example, let's say you try to
comb it all counterclockwise around some
axis. Then at the top and the bottom,
you end up with these little swirls and
the hair at the center-most point of
those swirls would have nowhere to go.
It's forced to stick up.
It's actually very fun to play around
with this in your mind, where no matter
how you try to flatten out the hair, it
is a mathematical guarantee that you
will be left with at least one tuft like
this.
In fact, even getting it down to just a
single problem point as opposed to two
is a bit of a challenge. It is possible
and if you like puzzles, I encourage you
to try thinking of how it could work.
Later on in this video, I'm going to
show you at least one way you can think
about doing it. For the moment though, I
imagine there's a more burning question,
which is that you might be wondering why
a mathematician would care about combing
fluffy spheres like this. And of course,
the answer is they don't. The name and
the informal statement are a bit
tongue-in-cheek. I will of course share
the more formal statement and in fact,
my real reason for making this video is
to share an unusually elegant way to
prove it, [music] one that I think will
delight any math lovers. But before any
of that, let's motivate things with an
example of the kind of situation where
these fluffy spheres naturally arise in
practice, in a context that initially
seems completely unrelated.
Okay, so imagine that you are a game
developer and you're programming some
game where you have a 3D model of an
airplane and what you want is to be able
to take an arbitrary trajectory for this
plane to fly along, presumably something
user-defined, and your job is to write a
function that orients the plane
correctly as it moves along that
trajectory.
So, for example, let's say you're at a
given point on some given trajectory.
You obviously want to move the center of
the model to be on that point, but
you're left with ambiguity on how it
should be rotated in 3D space.
The obvious constraint here is that you
know the nose of that plane should point
along the tangent vector of the path,
but even that leaves some ambiguity. How
is the plane rotated about this
nose-to-tail axis? One way you can think
about defining that last degree of
freedom is in terms of where this
perpendicular vector, along the left
wing direction, points. The task for
you, as the programmer of this video
game, is to figure out what that
perpendicular wing direction should be
at every single point along a given
trajectory.
Now, there is a correct way to do this,
which would involve calculating the
second derivative of the trajectory,
working out how to get this to match the
lift force from the wings together with
gravity, but maybe that seems a little
complicated right now. Resourceful and
lazy programmer that you are, you might
think, "Hey, is there just some
reasonable thing I can do to choose some
wing direction that's perpendicular to a
given velocity vector, the heading
direction of the plane?"
Here's one way you might think about it.
All of the possible ways this plane
could point in space, the various
heading directions that I'm coloring in
red, make up the points of a unit
sphere. What you want is to write a
function that takes in a given vector on
this sphere and returns some choice for
a vector perpendicular to it, the ones
that I'm coloring in pink. The only real
constraint is that you want this
association to be continuous. Otherwise,
it would mean the plane's orientation
could sharply jump, [music] which would
be a very clear glitch in the game. And
if you know nothing else, it really
feels like this should be a possible
task. After all, for a given heading
direction, you are not starved for
choices. You have infinitely many wing
directions to choose from, an entire
circles worth of options. So, how hard
could it be to make some reasonable
choice for every point on the sphere
that varies continuously? You might see
where I'm going with this. Choosing a
perpendicular direction like this is
equivalent to choosing a unit tangent
vector to that point of the sphere. So,
if you're assigning a specific
perpendicular to every possible
direction that plane could be pointed,
that's basically the same thing as
defining a tangent vector at every point
on a sphere. Now, this is starting to
look a little bit more like a hairy
ball. And in fact, now is as good a time
as any to step back and describe what
the hairy ball theorem actually says
more formally. If you have a sphere and
you choose some point on that sphere and
a plane tangent to the sphere at that
point, then any vector that you choose
within that plane, which is rooted at
that point, is called a tangent vector
of the sphere. If you assign a tangent
vector to every single point on the
sphere, one for each possible tangent
plane, we call it a vector field on the
sphere. And whenever you're drawing
vector fields like this, it's always
standard to scale the vectors down so
that you can avoid clutter. And the
other thing to keep in mind is that even
though an illustration like this
necessarily only shows a finite set of
vectors, rooted at a finite set of
points on the sphere, of course a vector
field consists of infinitely many
vectors, one for every single point on
the continuous surface.
So, the theorem, our main character for
today, states that if your vector field
is continuous, meaning there are no
sudden jumps in its direction, then it
must have at least one point with a null
vector, meaning a vector whose length is
zero.
For example, look back at our 3D model
case. The function that I was using for
many of the animations there was
essentially trying to keep the roof of
the plane pointed as upward as possible.
And when you express this function as a
vector field, where again each possible
direction for the nose of the plane is
thought of as a point on the sphere, and
each corresponding wing direction is
thought of as a tangent vector at that
point of the sphere, then it turns out
that function I was using gives a vector
field that spirals around the vertical
axis.
This actually does give reasonable
enough animations in most cases, but the
problem is that it has a discontinuity
at the poles. So, if ever I let the
plane point straight up or straight down
using this function, you would get this
glitching behavior as it passes through
that direction.
Now, if you're just a programmer messing
around with this, you might think you
can tweak things to avoid glitches like
that, but actually, the hairy ball
theorem guarantees, no matter how clever
you are, you are doomed to have some
direction producing this kind of glitch.
So, for robust animations, you cannot
simply use the direction of the nose of
the plane to determine its full
orientation. You have no choice but to
step back and incorporate more
information from the trajectory than the
velocity vector alone.
As another example, think about the wind
velocity at every point on the Earth,
say, at some constant altitude. A pretty
reasonable assumption is that wind
velocity varies continuously, so the
hairy ball theorem should apply. The
wind pattern I'm animating here is
completely unrealistic from a
meteorological standpoint, but the point
is that whatever wind pattern you dream
up, realistic or not, the hairy ball
theorem is going to guarantee that there
is always one place on the Earth for a
given altitude where the wind velocity
is exactly zero.
Now, if we're being pedantic, [music]
you could say atmosphere's
three-dimensional, so the more accurate
statement would be that the component of
wind velocity parallel to the ground is
zero. You know, it could be going
straight up or straight down, but still,
it is kind of counterintuitive.
A slightly more pragmatic example is if
you want a radio signal that is
completely identical in every direction
of 3D space, in the sense that everyone
a given distance away from the source
receives an identical radio wave, same
phase and amplitude at all points of
time. That might seem like a reasonable
objective, but if you know a little bit
about electromagnetic waves, you'll know
that they are oscillations in two
distinct vector fields, the electric and
the magnetic fields specifically.
Importantly, the direction of
oscillation for each one of these fields
is always perpendicular to the direction
of propagation, at least far away from
the source.
So, think about what that means. At a
given distance away from the source,
either one of these fields looks like a
tangent vector field on the sphere. And
the hairy ball theorem states at least
one point of that vector field has to be
zero. So, the only way to have a
completely identical signal in every
direction of 3D space is for the signal
itself to be zero, which presumably
defeats the point.
I bring up these examples just to say
that this seemingly playful fact about
fluffy spheres really does pop up in
unusual places. But, what I really want
to do with this video, the fun that I
want to have, is to let you explore this
idea the way that a pure mathematician
might. First, that puzzle that I
mentioned at the start actually gives a
really great way to flex your mind and
see how what feels obvious is not always
true. And then after that, I want to
share a completely beautiful proof that
explains why this theorem is true.
So, to the puzzle. I don't know about
you, but when I was first playing around
with this idea in my mind to build some
intuition, it was really not at all
obvious that reducing to a single null
point is even possible. For most of the
vector fields I could dream up, you get
at least one swirl going one way and
another swirl going the other way. Or
maybe a source at one point and a sink
at another. This makes it really
tempting to suggest that there should be
some universal law about needing at
least two different null points with
something opposite about them that has
to cancel out. Something like the north
and south poles of a magnet. Tempting as
that is, with a little cleverness, it is
possible to get just one null point.
And a nice way to define this is by
using something known as a stereographic
projection, where every point on the
sphere, except for the north pole, gets
mapped to a unique point on the XY
plane.
The way this works is very pretty. You
imagine a light shining from that north
pole, and every ray of light that passes
some point on the sphere, also hits one
and only one point of the XY plane. And
it goes the other way around, too. Every
point of the XY plane corresponds to a
unique point on that sphere, meaning
that plane can get mapped onto every
point of the sphere, except for the
north pole. This is a favorite mapping
among mathematicians, and the way we can
use it here is to imagine having some
vector field on the XY plane
>> [music]
>> that's never zero. That's simple enough
to define. You could just take a
constant vector field always pointing
one unit to the right. If you project
that vector field back onto the sphere,
this gives you something that's non-zero
everywhere, except for the north pole.
Admittedly, the way I'm showing it right
now makes it kind of hard to parse what
exactly is going on around that north
pole. The basic reason is that if you
take a uniform sample of points on the
plane,
>> [music]
>> they get infinitely dense around that
north pole under this projection. So,
let me show you a second way I could
illustrate things, which also, by the
way, lends itself to a more rigorous
definition for what I even mean by
projecting a vector field onto a sphere
like this. Imagine a fluid flowing on
the plane with a uniform velocity 1 unit
per second to the right. And then,
consider what the projection of each
particle of that fluid would look like
on the sphere during its motion. If you
take the velocity vectors for those
projected particles on the sphere, that
defines the vector field that I'm
talking about.
And illustrated this way, you can really
nicely see how the flow lines all form
perfect circles on the sphere, all of
which are mutually tangent with the
velocity of zero at that North Pole. It
really is a lovely projection.
The point is, even if initial mental
play and intuition might suggest that
vector fields on a sphere have to have
at least two null points, a little
creativity can give you a field that
just has one.
So, how do you know that it stops there?
How can you rigorously prove that no
matter how clever and creative you are,
it is simply not possible to define a
continuous vector field without forcing
at least one point to have a zero
vector?
This is where the real cleverness kicks
in.
The way that we're going to approach
this is with a proof by contradiction,
meaning you will assume that such a
non-zero vector field on the sphere is
possible and then deduce that something
impossible would have to follow.
Like I said, the argument I want to show
is just really beautiful and I think
it's made all the more so if you feel
like it's something you could have
discovered for yourself. So, as always,
please do pause and ponder whenever you
feel like you see the key idea.
This argument is not my own. It came my
way via the mathematician Sanja
Schedvasser, who also very kindly put
together the following animation to
illustrate the core idea. The basic
outline is that if such a non-zero
continuous vector field really did
exist, you could use it to create a
continuous deformation of the sphere
that turns that sphere inside out. And
then, we're going to prove why it's
actually impossible to turn a sphere
inside out, at least in a certain manner
of speaking. It's at this point that
viewers of classic math YouTube will be
yelling at their screens, but bear with
me. I promise I will get to that.
>> [music]
>> Okay, so this continuous deformation is
a little weird to define, but here's how
it works. Imagine that your sphere is
centered at the origin for some
coordinate system in 3D space.
For a given point on that sphere,
consider the vector attached to that
point, the one from our vector field. If
you slice the sphere along a plane,
which is defined by that vector and the
radial line to the origin, the plane
intersects the sphere at a certain great
circle, meaning a circle that's also
centered at the origin. What you're
going to do is let that point of the
sphere move along this circle in the
direction of that initial vector until
it gets precisely halfway around. So,
just to be clear, I'm not saying that it
flows along the general vector field of
the sphere. Its motion is entirely
determined just by the one vector that
it started out on.
The two important facts to highlight are
that it ends up on the negative of where
it started. And then also, because its
motion is entirely defined by what
vector it started on, and because we're
assuming the whole vector field is
continuous, nearby points are going to
have nearby trajectories. Right now, I'm
just showing you one point moving along
its prescribed half-circle path, but we
could just as well highlight a handful
of other points on the sphere, each of
which has its own vector associated with
it, each of which defines a great circle
to walk along, and you could watch all
of those points wander along the
assigned paths. Now, remember, we're
assuming that the vector field is
nonzero everywhere. We hope to
contradict that, but that's the
assumption. And what that means is that
every single point on the infinite
continuous sphere has a similarly
well-defined trajectory. So, naturally,
you want to see what it looks like for
the entire sphere to undergo that
motion. But, it's at this point that
animations become a little tricky
because of something intrinsically
paradoxical about illustrating a proof
by contradiction.
>> [music]
>> Think about it. We want to show what
this motion looks like as defined by
some hypothetical vector field that is
nonzero everywhere. But, of course, the
whole point is that no such vector field
exists. As the next best thing, we're
going to use that special vector field
that we just defined that has only a
single null point at the North Pole.
That way, if we chop away the North
Pole, we can at least see the kind of
thing that this motion would do to most
of the sphere, even if there's something
impossible about this being applied to
all of the sphere.
I'll go ahead and remove the vectors
themselves to avoid clutter, and this
right here is what it looks like for
every point on the surface to undergo
that bizarre specially defined motion.
Each one marching along its own
half-circle path defined by whatever
vector it started on.
And actually, that's kind of confusing
to follow. So, let me roll back the
clock a bit here, where you see that the
whole sphere ends up awkwardly crossing
through itself. To clarify things, we
might perturb the motion a little by
letting the radius of the points vary
during the motion. And it also makes
things clearer if we widen out that hole
on the top. This makes it much, much
easier to follow. At least for this
subset of the sphere, you can clearly
see two important features of the
motion.
Number one, the sphere gets turned
inside out. Number two, at no point in
time does any part of the sphere cross
the origin.
And that should make sense. Each
individual point is just following a
half-circle centered at the origin. So,
of course, it never passes through the
origin. Those are the two key
ingredients. For our proof, what we want
to say is that these two facts are
somehow incompatible. Before we can do
that though, we need to linger on this
first point. Why exactly does this
motion turn the sphere inside out? And
actually, what do we even mean by the
phrase inside out here? And in fact, let
me start with an even more basic
question. If you're standing at some
point on the sphere, how do you know
which way is outside and which way is
inside? [music]
I realize that might sound like a very
dumb question. You might say, "Just look
at whichever way is pointed away from
the origin. What's wrong with you?"
The real conundrum here though comes
from the fact that we intend to let the
surface warp and deform and get all
manipulated in some crazy way. So,
really what you want is a clear notion
of what we mean by inside and outside
that remains clear even after you
manipulate and massage and contort the
whole surface however you dream up.
The easiest way to do this, I think, is
going to be something familiar to any
graphics programmers, which is that you
start by assigning a coordinate system
to the sphere, something like our usual
notion of latitude and longitude. The
image you should have in your mind is
that every point of the sphere has a
little label attached to it with a pair
of numbers.
And importantly, these labels could
follow along during any motion or
manipulation you apply to the sphere.
Around a given point, consider the
direction of increasing longitude and
constant latitude, and draw a tangent
vector in that direction. And then draw
a line of increasing latitude with
constant longitude, and draw a tangent
vector in that direction. From here, the
way we define orientation is using
what's known as the right-hand rule. You
can point your index finger along that
first vector, and your middle finger
along that second vector, and then when
you stick out your thumb, it'll be
perpendicular to both. Notice, using our
right hand, the thumb is pointed
outside. And in fact, this is how we are
going to define what we even mean by
outside, at least with respect to the
given coordinate system. Doing this at
every point, you get what are known in
the business as unit normal vectors. As
a reference, these are very important in
computer graphics, where, for example,
they let you compute how light should
reflect off of a given surface. And for
our story, the thing we care about is
how, no matter how you manipulate or
warp the surface, because that
coordinate system you give to it can
kind of come along for the ride,
you can always play this game of
pointing your index finger along the
direction where the first coordinate
increases, and your middle finger along
the direction where that second
coordinate increases, and sticking out
your thumb.
It's otherwise surprisingly tricky to
define what you mean by inside and
outside in a way that naturally follows
along for any function.
So, why are we doing this? Think now
about that strange deformation induced
by a vector field on the sphere. How can
we conclude beyond any doubt that this
must turn the sphere inside out?
Well, remember how each individual point
starting at P ends up at negative P.
The much more straightforward way to get
there, literally, would be to reflect
through the origin like this.
So, consider that picture that we just
had of an example point together with
the oriented lines of latitude and
longitude passing through it. Notice
what it looks like if we let every point
in that diagram move over to its
negative. Again, you might imagine all
the coordinate labels of the surface
kind of riding along with it. So, when
you play the same game of pointing your
index finger in the direction where that
first coordinate increases and your
middle finger in the direction where
that second coordinate increases, now,
after everything has been negated,
notice that your thumb is pointing
towards the origin instead of away.
This is all to say, the function that
maps every point P of a sphere to its
negative necessarily turns the sphere
inside out in the sense of reversing
orientation the way we just defined it.
In particular, that very weird
deformation that we described in terms
of a hypothetical vector field must
reverse orientation because it's mapping
each point P to negative P.
You can also see this effect with a much
simpler motion that gets us to the same
final place. Imagine rotating the sphere
180° around the Z axis and then
reflecting through the XY plane. That
results in every point P landing on its
negative, and notice how all the unit
normal vectors that started pointing
outward end up [music] pointing inward.
And as it's rendered here with a blue
exterior and a brown interior, those two
colors end up getting swapped.
And it's at this point that viewers of
classic math videos all might be
bringing to mind an absolute banger of a
video that was produced in 1994 by the
geometry center at the University of
Minnesota. This is really one of the
true classics in all of math exposition.
It walks through this mind-blowing way
to turn a sphere inside out using a
certain continuous deformation. The
reason I bring this up for any of you
who watched that is to say that the
context there was a little bit
different. The phenomenon that they were
trying to avoid was creating cusps and
creases on the sphere during the
process.
But over here, for our purposes, we
don't really care about that. However,
there is one feature of our bizarre
vector field-induced deformation that
really would be impossible. No point of
the sphere ever passes through the
origin.
And there is a very beautiful way to see
why turning a sphere inside out without
crossing the origin just could never
happen. Maybe the most fun way to
illustrate this is with a physical
model. Imagine a fountain at the origin
spewing out water uniformly in all
directions, say at a rate of 1 L every
second. The way I'm animating it here is
with a bunch of droplets spewing away,
but in principle, I want you to think of
this as a continuous flow of an
incompressible fluid, something uniform
in all directions, and with that
incompressibility, we'll imagine that
the density of water through all of
space stays constant. That's important.
If you have some oriented surface,
something like our sphere with its unit
normal vectors, you can measure how much
water is flowing through that surface
per unit time. Physicists have a special
name for this. They call it the flux,
where on a given patch of area, the flux
measures how much water passes through
it per second, and you count it as
positive when the water flows from
inside to outside, aligned with the unit
normal vectors of the surface. Whereas,
flux would be negative if it's going the
other way, going against those normal
vectors.
When you add all of this up over the
whole surface, this gives you the total
flux. And the key observation is that
this total flux has to match the amount
of water being produced inside the
surface, that 1 L per second. And the
cool part is that this will remain true
even if you warp or deform the sphere
just a little bit. That total flux stays
at 1 L per second even if the flux
through a particular patch of area
changes during the process. And the
basic reason is that we're treating the
water as an incompressible fluid with a
constant uniform density through space.
So, every little bit of water produced
at the origin has to be canceled out by
one that is exiting the surface.
Importantly, for what I just said to be
true, we have to be counting flux with a
sign. For example, let's say you warp
the sphere so that it kind of folds over
itself like this. Then you'll notice
along a certain line, the water goes out
of the surface and then back into it and
then back out again. So, you would want
to count this flux as positive whenever
it goes from inside to outside, but
negative when it goes from outside to
inside so that you're not counting those
particles three different times. And
from here, you can maybe see the key
point I'm getting at towards our
contradiction. The only way that you
could ever change the net flux through a
surface like this is if part of that
surface crosses through the origin. For
example, if you pull it over to the side
so that it doesn't include the source at
all, the net flux would be zero. There
are as many water molecules flowing in
as there are flowing out. So, with that
in mind, think about everything we've
been talking about. If you could define
this non-zero vector field on a sphere
that lets you create this bizarre
deformation that turns the sphere inside
out, what happens to the flux?
Well, what we mean by turning the sphere
inside out is that all the unit normal
vectors end up pointing inside instead
of outside.
So, for any particular patch of area, at
some point the flux through it
transitions from being positive to
negative, and overall, at the end, that
total flux would have to end at -1 L/s.
But, at the same time, if it never
crosses the origin, the net flux can
never change. It starts at +1, so it has
to end at +1.
This is the contradiction. No
deformation with these two properties
can possibly exist. And there you have
it. A non-zero continuous vector field
on the sphere would be impossible. You
truly cannot comb a hairy ball. I don't
know about you, but I think that is so
beautiful. Very often topology is this
game where seemingly intuitive facts
have these surprising, but kind of
frustrating counterexamples. But, the
real insights and the creativity often
comes from the other side of the coin,
where you take something that seems
intuitive, but you find the construction
that really justifies why it's
fundamentally true. Now, there is more
to say about making the argument I just
showed you fully rigorous, and also more
to say about how this whole thing does
and does not generalize to other
dimensions.
But, before that, if you'll indulge me
in shifting gears entirely for a minute
here, I want to tell you about an
experimental new thing that I'm starting
up this year, which I'm thinking of as a
kind of virtual career fair. If you go
to 3b1b.co/talent,
what you'll find is a set of companies
that have two things in common. The
first one, essentially by definition, is
that they are interested in recruiting
from this audience. They value the kind
of mathematical and technical curiosity
clearly to be found in someone like you
who's watching a video like this for
fun. If you go and you explore the page
and you see the kind of puzzles and
challenges and technical work that each
one has chosen [music] to share with
you, you'll pretty quickly get a sense
of the shared values here. The second
thing they have in common is that the
people working there really love what
they do. And this one's important to me.
I was pretty careful about it while
setting this whole thing up because all
of this only makes sense to do if it's
actually valuable to the audience. So, I
took some time to sit down and chat with
the technical teams at each group, and
inclusion only really made sense if they
clearly like what they do. Pretty
universally, a core reason that the
people enjoyed their work was out of a
very sincere respect for all of their
teammates. In the hopes of making this
relevant to you, whoever you might be,
there is a range of job types available
across a range of industries, including
senior roles, new careers, internships,
or even part-time tutoring gigs.
For broader context, if you're curious,
I recorded a whole video on the second
channel explaining why I started this,
what the deal is. One thing that I
mentioned over there is how I'm looking
to make a few hires myself, and whenever
this is the case, I will include my own
page up on this virtual career fair,
where you can go and find the
description of what I'm looking for and
the applications. The whole page will
stay updated as time goes on, so even if
you're not looking for a job now, but
you are sometime in the future, be sure
to check it out.
All right, so back to the hairy ball
theorem. The argument at the end rested
on this whole idea of flux, which
admittedly is a little hand-wavy without
further details. So, I'll leave up on
screen a set of exercises outlining one
way that you could make this more
rigorous if you have a background with
multivariable calculus and the
divergence theorem. There is another
deeper way to get at the same basic idea
using something called a homology group,
but that one is certainly beyond the
scope for today. The last point I want
to leave you pondering on is the nature
of other dimensions. It's not hard to
see that you can comb down the hairs on
a fluffy circle, even though you can't
do it for a sphere. And in general, the
rule is that spheres in all of the even
dimensions can be combed down, but those
in all of the odd-numbered dimensions
cannot. Now, what I like about the
argument that we just talked about for
this whole video is that it offers a
pretty direct clue for why that's the
rule, at least if you're comfortable
with the notion of orientation. In all
of the even dimensions, the function
that maps a point to its negative is an
orientation-preserving function, whereas
in all of the odd dimensions, that's an
orientation reversing function. You
might enjoy taking a moment to pause and
ponder on why that means the proof we
just outlined works in all of the odd
dimensions. And even though it doesn't
explicitly tell you that nothing could
work in the even dimensions, it's a fun
puzzle to see if you can construct an
explicit example of a non-zero vector
field in all of those even dimensions.
For example, how do you comb down the
hairs on a hypersphere in four
dimensions?